this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
hello and welcome to software
engineering radio my name is nikhil and
your guest host for this episode today I
will be speaking with Dietrich Ayala
about ipfs Dietrich leads the browsers
and platforms group at protocol Labs
making a more trustworthy and Reliant
web through the adoption of ipfs
filecoin and lib P2P in browsers open
source libraries developer Tools Mobile
apps operating systems and space
Communications before protocol Labs he
spent over a decade at Mozilla building
Firefox shipping a smartphone OS and
running programs to scale developer
relationships globally datrix first
computer job was as a webmaster at Indie
music Label sub-pop records doing
anything and everything digital he has
since worked at small startups and also
household names like McAfee and Yahoo
before computerizing Dietrich was a
barista and Chef welcome to the show
Dietrich and is there anything I might
have missed in your bio that you would
like to add
thanks for having me no I think that
pretty well covers it I started doing
programming pretty late in my mid to
late 20s and did all kinds of fun things
than in order to get there flash 3 php3
going way back wow yeah it sounds like
you've gone through the gamut so let's
jump into the topic of the day which is
ipfs or to quote its full form
interplanetary file system
so Dietrich could you give us an
overview of what is ipfs
yeah ipfs is a protocol for the
distribution of data similar to how HTTP
is a protocol for the distribution of
data things that it's used for today
quite often are publishing web pages the
availability of very large data sets and
also things like local subnet
communication between applications one
of the differences between ipfest and
http
that's important is that HTTP uses a
trust model of SSL DNS combined with
with HTTP to be able to find and locate
data whereas ipvs uses content
addressing using the unique signature of
the data itself as the address that we
requested by and this means that your
phone can be a server or another
computer on the subnet computer server
or a remote computer on the other side
of the world and also be a server of the
data that you're looking for on the ipfs
network
awesome so you mentioned that ipfs is a
protocol similar to http so HTTP
obviously has a long long pedigree it's
been there it's been adopted as a
standard what is the status of ipfs in
terms of the adoption as the protocol
spec ipfs itself has
been I think for seven years at this
point so it's not necessarily new but I
think it definitely was an experimental
phase for a long time one of the major
changes that we've seen in this last two
years maybe as a real uptick in adoption
for a couple of different use cases the
biggest one definitely in the last year
year and a half is nfts when you have a
digital asset and it's metadata that you
want to be able to live outside of a
specific HTTP endpoint or server
something not tied to a specific DNS and
URL you need to have some way to
identify it and make sure that it can be
available everywhere ipfs fit that bill
pretty well being that you can address
the content by its signature not by a
specific server location so that
definitely a large draw on ipfs usage
from that Community blockchains
generally you want to write to an
immutable Ledger something that isn't
going to change or get pulled out from
under you if somebody forgets to renew
their update their lead certificates or
changes companies or you know any or
even maybe just moves files in a
directory
in HTTP you get a 404 in ipfs you still
have this ID where if that data is still
available from someone on the network
it's going to be findable and therefore
those addresses end up being of high
utility to things like blockchains
So speaking of blockchains there is this
well-publicized blockchain called
filecoin which has a good relationship
or is kind of but leverages ipfs can you
speak a little bit about the
relationship between filecoin and ipf
ipfs yeah sure so filecoin and ipfs use
some similar components they use content
IDs that's what we call ipfs addresses
these these content addressable bits
they also use lip P2P which is a toolkit
for building peer-to-peer applications
it's a set of specifications that can be
implemented in every any programming
language some of the big ones that we
use a lot are the go implementation and
the JavaScript implementation and
filecoin is a level one blockchain so it
is its own Standalone blockchain where
mining is comprised of file storage
operations so what on another blockchain
like ethereum or Bitcoin you would call
miners we call Storage providers
and the activity on the network is
comprised of a couple different things
proving that they have storage capacity
and proving that they're still holding
the data that you ask them to store
ipfs and filecoin are not dependent on
each other you can use ipfest and never
use filecoin or its blockchain for
anything at all you can use filecoin to
be able to store data very large data
it's designed initially for very large
data sets the default storage deal size
is 32 gigabytes so definitely not just
for storing a couple of images and you
can do that without ever publishing that
data to ipfast it could be that you just
want to securely store that data with
one or more different storage providers
possibly in different Geographic
locations for redundancy and safety
purposes and get it back maybe a few
years later but you never have to
publish that to ipfest and that does not
happen by default so the two can be used
in complementary ways but are completely
decoupled and are not do not require the
use of the other
right so as you pointed out ipfs is not
coupled with filecoin and you you can
use one or the other in complementary
ways can you also so does that mean that
I can take ipfs the ipfs technology and
incorporate it into my own blockchain
for example or can I even just leverage
ipfs to build a web application for
example is that one of the things that
are possible with ipfs yeah absolutely
you can do both of those things some
blockchains or blockchain based projects
do bundle an ipfs node which is way of
talking about kind of like the fullest
expression of the capabilities of iqfs
Aragon was a project based on making it
easy to be able to create a dow a
decentralized autonomous organization
out of the box using their application
they bundled ipfs with it one of the
places that we're seeing a lot of uptake
of ipfs is like you're saying people
wanted to serve web pages on on the
network work and this kind of happens
for a couple of interesting reasons
I think the regular web the HTTP web is
something that like you said that's been
around for over 30 years now all of our
tools speak HTTP our apis speak HTTP
we're all used to the pain and the
peculiarities of that stack everything
from you know having to understand the
full stack itself which is a really
massive complex set of Technologies and
also everything that's required to be
able to deploy to http and we get used
to the things that can go wrong updating
us at cell service moving files around
changing your whole back end even trying
to manage and collaboratively manage
things like DNS at an organization
challenges but challenges that other
companies have filled those gaps with
and with ipfs there's a an aspect of DIY
to it right now where you can do it at
production levels and then a bunch of
companies do this today but also for the
regular developer that wants to publish
a web page or even a non-technical
person that wants to publish a static
HTML Zine or a bunch of images they can
do that with ipfs in a way that doesn't
require them to go and set up a remote
service somewhere register a DNS name
and do all these things they can add it
to a local ipfs node IPS desktop is a
very easy one to install an electron
based app generally for for
non-technical users not too bad to
upload files to and then share those
addresses with with other people those
addresses often points to an ipfs
Gateway we do run IPS gateways to the
HTTP Network that allows people to
easily access files on the ipps network
from web browsers and that's a a big
goal for us is to really get native
support for iqbs inside web browsers and
you know with my background working at
Mozilla for a long time before joining
political Labs is something that I've
been focused on over this last couple of
years okay great so the way I understand
it from you is that you are it is
possible to leverage ipfs and build put
files on ipfs and use it for your web
application and you can easily upload
files to ipfs but you still need a way
to kind of distribute it and right now
basically that's over HTTP and you have
an HTTP to ipfs converter the protocol
Labs is running that helps you kind of
make that translation so you can you can
run your web application for the most
part that's right but I think that last
way to http so the go laying
implementation of ipfs comes with that
Gateway feature you can turn it on that
means that you can run a Gateway we
actually have a website called the
public Gateway Checker that allows you
to list your gateway if you're running
one protocolab says run iqs.io and
dweb.link two different gateways for
some time but one of the biggest out
there is cloudflares cloudflare runs an
ibvis Gateway and serves really a lot of
data through there and we're seeing more
and more providers run I think this
gateways as part of their infrastructure
for distributed Web projects to be able
to serve things like nfts and to be able
to serve the needs of growing blockchain
usage
right so just to kind of quickly double
click that on that a little bit so
cloudflare is a well-known CDN content
delivery Network and they host files
regularly for everybody so when if I
when you said I can leverage cloudflare
to use ipfs is that something that I can
consciously you know is there a setting
in Cloud fair that I can just tell them
no I want to use ipfs for my application
or is this something that they're doing
internally transparently as a
value-added service to all customers
and yes for right now they're running a
HTTP gateway to the ipfs network that
anybody can access and load data through
and this is one of the interesting
things that kind of uh what are the
paradigmatic differences between ipfs
and HTTP with HTTP you can only Access
Data from a publisher
through their website which is the
intersection of that DNS name the SSL
certificate often these days and the
HTTP servers or cdns that they are
running and if that company decides you
know that they don't want to serve that
data anymore that data is gone from the
internet I think the original research
that rooster kale and internet archive
did around the average lifetime of web
page was in the late 90s and even then
it was like it's like somewhere between
60 and 90 days and these days with you
know like native apps and apis and
things like that a lot of the you know
information on the regular web doesn't
actually last that long and one of the
things that ipfest does is because you
can address data on the network
and get it from anyone on the network
through the peer-to-peer part of it you
could ask for the same address from
cloudflare's Gateway
or the iqvest.io Gateway or the local
node that you may be running maybe you
even have a local HTTP Gateway running
on your computer all of them can fetch
that address from the network from
whoever might be holding it so with HTTP
you can get as long as someone on the
network out there somewhere is hosting
that one file that you asked for
and you ask cloudflare us your own node
they will all be able to fetch that file
from that one person out there who's
hosting it that makes for a level of
resiliency that you can't have today
with HTTP Yeah so basically when that
that implies that okay I set up my
account with cloudflare and my account
for whatever reason is closed or shut
down or it runs out of money or whatever
I can still run my website as long as
some one of the other gateways has I
mean I can submit that CID to one of the
other gateways yeah I mean right now you
don't even need a cloudflare cloud
account to be able to do that let's say
you when you install an ipfs node on
your desktop computer today or the
laptop or whatever and you add a file
there you get the address for that file
you can ask cloudflare's Gateway for it
and it will connect to the ipvs public
network which is a distributed hash
table it will ask all the other nodes on
the network or hopefully not all of them
will find it much sort of that based on
the academically algorithm that the ipfs
public DHT uses it will find the node as
efficiently as possible that is holding
that data the one on your computer that
you installed and are running
which will return that to cloudflare's
Gateway which will then return it to you
and that means that you can ask for the
same image from different HTTP servers
and because the address that you asked
for is cryptographically verifiable is
basically a sha-256 hash with some added
metadata
you can verify that the data you get in
return is the data you asked for
and that means you have to care a little
bit less about where it actually came
from so the side effect of that
addressing mechanism leads to a type of
resilience in that you can ask anybody
for the data that you need you can
receive it from anybody that has it and
you can verify that it was not modified
there's really interesting properties
that the HTTP web kind of doesn't have I
mean by by Design to some extent Dynamic
data on these two webs is one of the
reasons why we love it in use it right
but it's a maybe a different set of use
cases true true in fact actually you've
brought up a few terms and I think it's
now time to kind of like jump in a
little bit and talk about some of that
right so we mentioned things like CID
which is a Content identifier we talked
about DHT which is distributed hash
table and so maybe we can start from the
basics right so I have a file with me
right and it's a I don't know it's an
image of my profile and I want to upload
it and I want to upload it so when I
submit it into an ipfs your ipfs desktop
application to upload it what actually
happens to that file so does that mean
it uh can you can you describe a little
bit about how a file is converted into
something that can get uploaded into
ipfs Network yeah absolutely so let's
say you install IPS desktop and you're
running an ipfs code or maybe you did
Brew install or you went through npm or
chocolatey however you end up you know
want to run software locally ipfs the IP
the go laying implementation is
available in most of them these days
you're running ipfs locally and you add
that image file to it if that file is
under the the when I'll get there the
default block size uh let's say it's
under under a Meg that file will be
added to a local repository kind of like
your you know local git repositories
where it's a hidden hidden directory
with a set of files breaks these files
up in the chunks with signatures and
things like this the ipfs repository uh
has them metadated about the file but
the file doesn't go anywhere
it sits in that Repository
and what your ipfs node does is it has
it maintains a connection to the public
DHT of what we call often the IPS
Network that's a public network of
computers uh several hundred thousand I
think at this point maybe even more
actually no it's been been a while I
should have checked those numbers before
coming and talking to you so they could
send how big they are but the last check
was a couple hundred thousand computers
that everyone from us to cloudflare to
thousands of hobbyists to lots of
different companies that are running
ipfs nodes to run and it will ask it
well it will announce that it has your
file so it will generate that hash that
hash based address the CID we'll take
the scid and announce it to the network
it will say hey I've got this file that
has this or this data that has this
address and now that will be cached for
a temporary period of time across a
number of those nodes being like Oh now
we know that Nick Hills node has a file
with that address so then when people
ask for it later let's say you tell
let's say you then text that address to
me and I'm on the other side of the
planet and I go to my my cloudflare HTTP
gateway to the ipfs network or I used to
use my local ipfs node and I say get me
this file it will then go to the network
and ask hey does anybody have this file
and it maintains a connection like yours
does to a number of nodes and it will
ask those nodes it's connected to hey do
you know anybody that has this file and
it will then do that until it finds the
information about your node
it will then directly connect to your
node and ask it for that data your node
will return that data so when you add
something to the ipps network no data
immediately necessarily if you're
running your own node and it's on your
local machine is moved at all it just
announces to that low that that Network
at large the global one that locally you
do have something with that address on
it and if somebody else is asking for it
it will eventually respond to those
requests because it will receive them
through that public network that's kind
of the most basic sense how a single
file you can add it to your IPS node
publish it to the network which is
really more of an announce not actually
moving data anywhere and then respond to
request this really I hope demystifies
some of the magic that people think
about ipfest which is like oh if I add
data to ipfest how do I take it down
well most often IPS hosting actually
works a lot like traditional web hosting
though the person hosting the data is
you if you want like for me the max
maximum of IP addresses if you want your
data to stay available on the network
you need to ensure that it does so and
often this means using what we call a
pinning service a company that hosts
your data on ideas Network to make sure
that it stays available all the time the
same way that you would for a regular
web host so in some respects while ipfs
is you know as I say power automatically
different than HTTP in terms of how we
address data who you can get it from how
you can verify that was modified all
things that HTTP can't really do it also
does work like HTTP in that if you want
some data to stay available
you need to make sure that it does and
one of the major differences from a
deploymented scaling aspect and this you
know is something that is really
important characteristic of ipfest is
that with HTTP if you upload a file to
your HTTP web server and you serve that
that same image from you know
nikhilsblog.com
you are basically aside from them if
you're paying for cdns or caches or
things like that the the only
verifiable place that that data can be
retrieved from Forever that's the
ceiling of availability with HTTP well
with ipfs anybody hosting that file can
keep that file available on that Network
and so for ipfas you hosting it once is
the ceiling of availability of data is
the floor remain yeah yeah sorry it's
the floor I'm not in Australia I'm not
living in an upside down world
but yeah so really availability starts
by uploading one file once with ipfs but
it ends there with HTTP for the most
part okay right thank you for that
that's a it's a great description of the
how this kind of file gets published and
like you said it's the floor just a
couple of quick follow-ups over there so
how do I actually
setup copy so you mentioned a pinning
service is that something that I have to
use or can I kind of send you the file
and say you know hey this is my file I
want you to also host it put it in your
in your node and it would automatically
work and does that work yes actually one
of the when I first started working on
ipfest related things I was making a
browser extension that basically
kind of had some of the the underlying
common denominators The Primitives that
you would need inside a browser to be
able to build an ipfs client or adapt or
secure scuttlebuds other decentralized
web protocols or even a ethereum like
client or something like that and I
discovered ipfast and one of the first
projects I found was something called
ipfs with friends and it was the idea
that friends were sharing the data
amongst themselves in a way that allowed
them to have fun and collaborate and if
some service provider went away well you
and all your friends still had your team
or if they closed down your Channel or
or if they got bought by a bigger fish
or you know whatever that you and your
friends well you and your friends still
had your stuff because your stuff is
your stuff and I think for me that that
ends up being one of the kind of one of
the most fun aspects of of these
networks and these alternative ways of
thinking about collaborating with and
sharing data is that it becomes
cooperative and you can build
communities around it there's a I think
all active has cluster which actually
uses like a sync algorithm to be able to
sync data between different ibfs nodes
and what people have done with our
people's cluster is come up with this
idea of collaborative clusters where you
might want to contribute to the hosting
of critical data like a scientific data
set or Wikipedia data or these other
things that you might want to donate
serving from your ipfs node and be a
part of the community that keeps that
data available and alive so we've seen
lots and lots of instances of
collaborative data sharing in this way
without confess that you know with http
if you're requesting it from HTTP and
that one website goes down or you happen
to live in a country that that turns
that DNS off well you're out of luck
right so just to kind of get back to the
other point so we were so far talking
about one image file which was a
relatively small image file and just now
we talked about Wikipedia right which is
obviously a lot more data so how does
actually ipfs work with large files is
it like getting a hash of that entire
large file and distributing that or is
that is there something more complex
than that oh yeah more complex and more
interesting Big Data big problem and I
think in the cloud scaling world you
know maybe that looks like S3 egress
builds but for here ipfs has ways of
linking data and that are really
interesting and so let's say that that
image file that you have is a 10
megabyte image file well I give us
operates on the idea of blocks so up to
a Meg one megabyte it will just serve
that data as one address for that one
block of data if you have that file and
it's a 10 megabyte file when you add it
to your ipfs node what that local ipv
will do again without publishing any
data to the network yet it will chunk
that file it'll break break it up into
smaller chunks it will give each one of
those chunks an address
and then it will
encode that data into a Merkel dag which
is basically a data construct that Maps
the ideas of all of those blocks into
one walkable directed acyclic graph so
it's a way of linking all of those
chunks together so then you say ID over
there is that a hash ID of that block or
is that some other kind of ID is the
same it's a CID but it has a metadata
encoded into that block that says the
cids that are the leaf nodes ah okay
cool yeah it still ends up being an
immutable data structure but you can
reference those Blocks individually so
now let's say e on the other side of the
world I ask for the root CID the the
star at the tip of that tree and it goes
out and asks the network it finds your
computer and then it will ask for all of
the blocks going down that graph each
individual and this is really efficient
for a couple of different reasons one
might be immediately obvious which is
let's say someone else has some of those
blocks but not all the blocks I can now
start receiving those blocks from both
of you and you might serve me half the
blocks they might serve me half the
blocks and then you can get when you
think about very very large data sets
like Wikipedia 650 gigs or something
like that for like the base variable
image of it like or or a large operating
system just throws being distributed
over ipfs becomes very efficient at that
point this is similar to BitTorrent
isn't it isn't that that what BitTorrent
also does yeah at high level that
pattern is is very similar the way that
data addressing happens BitTorrent and
verification is quite different and also
the way that you basically advertise and
publish on the network is also quite
different but that same pattern
absolutely
okay so so we've got this Merkel dag of
hashes and now that is actually what is
getting published when you said you know
the file stays with you and it the thing
gets published the CID gets published
now it's a Merkel bag that gets
published it's still a CID though so
what it'll do is actually publish the
cids of each one of those blocks from
the roots all the way down to the leaf
nodes all those branch nodes it will it
will publish those the cids of each
block and that's how you get that
Network level efficiency but doesn't it
also have to publish the relationship
between the blocks which block is first
or which block is second yeah and that's
encoded into the block so ah it's
encoded into the block itself
that does mean more round trips and so
trade-offs right you end up getting some
resiliency in exchange for some
trade-offs you know something you will
notice I give us
it is not immediately in some cases as
fast as a centralized Network where
you're just asking one party for one
thing that you hope is not a 404 and
they actually have it and they just
return it to you if they have it big or
small nothing complex so performance is
definitely one of the challenges
performance on a distributed Network
well that's that's been a academic and
practical challenge for quite a long
time we've made huge strides in making
ipfest very very performant in different
applications in different contexts but
ultimately the type of performance that
end users need is relative to the
trade-offs that they have in their given
use case so for example if you want to
be able to get some data from somebody
on the local network but there's no
Internet available you could do that
with ipfs and it's going to be really
fast because it's going to have a local
network and you have no internet
connectivity so that in that use case
for example very useful whereas HTTP
you'd be like well it's on a server on
the internet somewhere but neither of us
have internet access so can't do
anything so we love we love this like
local collaboration is something that
you can do without too fast that the
it's really difficult like you can't
even get an SSL server for local network
addresses yeah that's been a process of
the w3c for many many years it's not
really going in right
so that just to kind of focus on the CID
thing so you mentioned one of everything
interesting which was that the CID is
got an encoding of some metadata about
the hash like what is the position of
the hash sorry what is the position of
the block that this particular CID is
addressing right so does that mean that
it's not like simple sha hash of the
file it uh it seems to imply that there
is more to it than just just a hash of
the file content the relationships in
that mercury tag and that structure is
not encoded in the CID
it's in the data that you guys back when
you ask for this Aid the CID itself
actually is that shot 256 hash by
default I mean it's but I I think this
is actually a great entry point into
what is the CID and a CID yes more than
just a hash it's basically a super
address that is designed to be
upgradable and configurable
so HTTP URLs today they're not
necessarily versions you could say hey I
support a conversion of HTTP and you can
do that you know in the beginning of
your HP request response but the URLs
themselves uh is a pretty static format
with cids you can configure the chunking
algorithm you can configure the hash
that you want to use if you don't want
to use shot to 56 you want to use
something else something you configure
and there's a set of specifications that
comprise these Technologies uh one is
multi-base one is multi-hash and these
are again feature proof upgradable data
construction specifications for these
different components of a CID and multi
hash and multi-baser both actually we're
going to propose them at the ITF to go
into draft status there so we really
want to standardize these what we see is
very important ingredients in Internet
that can be resilient for the next you
know not just the last 30 to 50 years
but the next 30 to 50 years in a way
that sure lets that data stay available
and resilient and malleable and
upgradable instead of being held back by
technologies that are location based
that maybe aren't as upgradable and be
very difficult to kind of like try to
bolt on functionality for upgradability
into things like HTTP I think we saw
this with off offline first movements
right it's very difficult to get it's a
protocol like HP which is designed about
remote request response exchange of data
to be thought of as offline and then
that I think that architectural mismatch
is still problematic today or
multi-party things like cores are a
great example of of like all right as
soon as you violate the trust boundaries
of the origin security model they should
be things get really really hard and we
have to be very very careful and things
have to be very very safe and difficult
and then people end up just not doing it
so much okay so speaking of cids again
the format that I've seen is one of the
arguments that you could make against it
is that it's not the most user-friendly
right it's not as easy as
www.example.com which is something that
you know rolls off the tongue so to
speak so is there a way for us to kind
of map these you know complex
multi-hashes to a more simpler naming
system that you know we could remember
and share with friends yeah there's a
bunch of different ways that people do
this so DNS link is one of them and
that's basically using DNS text records
to be able to point a traditional domain
name to an ipfs CID and that's something
that is used by a lot of different web
hosts that support ipfest today Fleek
dot Co is one and then even things like
ens and their name service sources like
this use Technologies like DNS and
another one called ipns which is a way
having a key that you can use and
publish a public key that represents a
pointer to a given CID so this is a
question that often comes up given that
a CID is immutable but let's say I want
to publish a new version of my profile
image the example used earlier you would
use something like ipns to say here's
the public record on the ipfs network
that is a mutable pointer to immutable
data so from a publishing standpoint web
developers are really familiar with
saying all right I'm going to set up my
DNS name and it's going to point to an
IP address and then up IP address I will
have my web server and that will serve
whatever I want out of there and I can
change it all I want with ipfast and
public naming the way they're talking
about we flip that model a little bit we
push the mutability from your web server
up to the DNS level so let's say you
publish new version of your static
website you use whatever your you know
Jam stack approach is you generate the
static HTML you publish it to your
regular website you also can then get
the ipfsc ID of that static content to
ipvs and update your DNS link and point
it to that new CID and that allows you
to be able to publish mutable data
Dynamic data on ipfs in a way that still
allows people to navigate it using their
user agents that they use today
typically a web browser right okay cool
so
from what I understood so that you have
the concept of the DNS link which has
the real regular HTTP DNS Concepts and
that maps to this ipns which is
essentially kind of like a pointer to
the actual CID which it kind of allows
you to then say hey okay I made a
mistake with my profile I've got a
better profile I want to update the
profile and so I can just update the CID
and change the pointer to point to that
new CID and then just share the DNS link
to my friend and he'll see the new
profile yeah they have to reload the
page I mean I wouldn't call this haircut
a mistake it was an improvement I needed
it
yeah absolutely yeah yeah Evan but we
all keep adding gray hairs and
experimenting with uh with color right
so moving on we talked about how you can
publish your file and it's not really
publishing the file you're basically
just putting a pointer out there the CID
out there we basically said that okay
it's up to you you should should take
that you don't copy the file or you
don't give the file to anybody you still
be only one copy what about folks that
are really interested like like you
pointed out like the Wikipedia folks or
the people who who want to keep internet
archive right they are very invested in
keeping
long I mean copies of data if they want
to have this working for a long time is
there any kind of limit or there is any
kind of minimal ceiling in the ipfs
protocol that says if you want to retain
you know keep this around for a long
time you should keep n number of copies
across y number of nodes or research
anything like that or is this just
generally right at this point well the
more you keep the better it is you know
there's a good question and something
that I've thought about doing some like
projecting or modeling but it's pretty
use case dependent it kind of depends on
what the level of demand is for the file
and what the use cases are for it so you
know if you have some like cold kind of
yeah cold storage data archives that you
aren't going to be requested very very
often and where you think that they're
generally pretty safe run by a business
or something maybe you have a copy
that's your published copy and one that
you keep in your own node or something
like that but I don't think there's a
hard and fast rule there and I think for
use cases you could come up with some
kind of availability but it would come
down it actually probably would start
looking like Global CDN availability
points of presence right if you want to
have data replicated and available
highly available for a geography where
there's given demand well you might want
to pick a ipps pinning provider that has
a presence in that geographic region and
then that makes sure that people using
iqbas can get that initial data more
easily available maybe you even use
something like ipfs cluster to be able
to sync that data out to the other nodes
that you want to have that data
available so we definitely see patterns
like that as different ipfest providers
and kind of ipfs providers as an
industry is growing people were
operating these nodes at scale this is
really something that is not nearly as
formalized and as well trodden round as
you know Cloud distribution and
Publishing and scaling today with HTTP
web so we have a community of people
that operated iqbs nodes that are
sharing information about how to do that
because IBS has a repository that local
repository though isn't doesn't really
operate the way that a database does
today but it's a storage space and it's
pretty it's pretty relatively simple
compared to a you know rdbms or object
database object-based database or
something like that so it definitely
it's a publishing and addressability
layer and a peer-to-peer Network in one
and scaling that yeah sometimes these
days still take some magic and and some
some dark parts of hanging out with
other people's operators and figuring
out what worked but I think that's one
of the biggest growth areas that we've
seen there are just now a bunch of
companies doing this and they weren't
doing this a year ago two years ago at
nearly the late the same scale and level
nft drops in particular you want to put
two thousand things up yeah like the
dependency on availability of that data
at a given time is crucial to be able to
do that job so there we're seeing like a
lot of a lot of interesting Innovations
happening around bulk uploads uh
availability times there's a group here
nft.storage that they're a team within
protocol labs and that might be turning
into a subsidiary at some point actually
they work together with cloudflare to
make ipvs data available in qualifier
Edge workers in really interesting ways
to be able to ensure the high
availability of nft assets and metadata
so there's some of these use cases are
really pushing on the state state of the
art and high availability performance
and distribution IPS data right okay
cool so it sounds like from what you
said the ipfs specification per se
doesn't actually have an opinion about
this this is kind of like a layer above
right so thinking about like when I when
I put my distributed systems cap on and
I come back and say hey okay is this
similar to your standard I don't know
Kafka or your standard database cluster
we are not talking about a system ipfs
works at a level lower than that and
then from what you're saying it looks
like these other Concepts like the ipfs
cluster and the node providers that are
working on top of it would be
potentially building these applications
that then become concerned about things
like the cap theorem and availability
and partitioning and stuff like that am
I right yeah I think that's probably a
good way of describing it right like I
think one of the conversations that
we've had a lot is what the most minimal
version of ipfs is do you need to
participate in the public DHT do you
need to actually have Lupita P do you
need to have a a transport agnostic
protocol layer underneath you and I
think what we've ended up at is that
content addressing using ipfsc IDs to
address data is really the minimum
requirement for Air quotes using ipfs if
you're addressing data in that way you
get a lot of the benefits and you kind
of get to choose how much of the
underlying infrastructure you want to
implement and how you get a way of
addressing data that can live beyond
that initial use case or even beyond the
initial publisher and that has its
trade-offs and challenges too but it
ensures that the application itself
doesn't have that location-based
complexity built into it it can still
address that data even if that data
lives somewhere else different data
center a different domain name so that
that use of that addressing also means
because you know that you can get that
data from anywhere because of that
cryptographic verifiability because the
address is generated from the data
itself if someone changes even one pixel
in that image it's going to have a
different address so you ask for
something and you can verify that what
you get in return is actually what you
ask for and that's built into how we
address data from the root of the
project so I think that's a really good
way of thinking about it that the
minimum viable ipfs is using cids
content identifiers that are based on
the contents of the data and really
outside of the stock from there we're
seeing all kinds of permutations of of
ipfest from highly centralized HTTP ipfs
data networks too where anybody can
still get that data but they get it from
a single Source you know is an
underlying PDP Network to private
networks so two or more computers that
have a private DHT between them and
they're sharing that data it's not
connected to the public network or even
transient and IQs networks where let's
say you and I have mobile is a really
good use case right let's say you and I
are in the same room there's no internet
well we're not going to run like a full
ipfs node realistically on our phone
because that's going to open up a bunch
of listening sockets and you know all
types of one it'll drain your battery
real fast trying to run a server like
that it's just not optimized for the
architecture of mobile devices or the
radio architectures of their network
connections either right but if you and
I have a ipfs based application that can
communicate over say ble or nearby or
even like the underlying Network bits
that iOS ships that power things like
airdrop if you're addressing data by
that CID we can still have an app that
completely communicates directly I can
share photos with you and we can be
typing into an app and chatting back and
forth even though there's no external
network at all right yeah and
potentially it could be more efficient
if there are if you're sharing files
that are similar and that have similar
blocks right absolutely we're actually
seeing some groups like apply this
towards things like refugee camps where
they can't get video and DNS resolution
outside of these places even though
there's great local network connectivity
and then other use cases like emergency
situations like earthquakes or something
like that where Municipal Services might
be down but you can do things like store
and forward messaging that are content
addressed over things like ipfs on
devices or through local Wi-Fi subnets
that are set up and things like this so
that resiliency I think is going to be
an asset in the long term you know that
I think right now we're still in still
in relatively early days of you know
under under a decade in the life of this
technology in terms of developer tooling
yeah High availability cloud deployments
like all this kind of stuff great I want
to kind of just also now delve into a
slightly different topic and this is
something that came up when I was kind
of looking into ipfs that is lib b2p
right so my understanding essentially is
that ipfs essentially from a code
organization perspective is a bundle of
different and components right so you
have lip b2p and you have the multi-hash
concepts and then you have ipld and
unixfs and stuff like that let me to be
basically can you kind of go into what
it is and what did that what does it
have to do with ipfs what is the
relationship between the two yeah so
libidity p is a toolkit for building
peer-to-peer applications and I think
the best way to think about it is to
think about how would you build
applications that are transport agnostic
and that's that's about P2P necessarily
but where your application layer has a
consistent API that it can use to be
able to communicate with the network
whatever Network that is the underlying
Network could be Bluetooth LE between
two phones the underlying Network could
be a you know the the internet itself
where you have TCP and UDP and all these
you know protocols that can operate at
high scale the underlying Network could
be mqtt only on a iot sensor Network
with lipid to P you have a an
obstruction layer where you can write
application code that doesn't have to
care about those underlying network
connectivity specifics or network
transport availability specifics
necessarily maybe the initial author is
inflated onto the hardware and figures
not bit out but as the at the
application layer you don't have to do
so as much and so this has a lot of
benefits in reducing complexity at the
layer above and be able to have
application code that is portable across
maybe some of these different runtimes
and is not locked into things like
checking for HTTP headers or anything
like that right there's a benefits
regardless of if you're building web
applications If You're Building Systems
code and tools but also it's not
required for ipfest you can we're seeing
more and more ipms implementations that
don't necessarily bundle all of libiddp
itself is a in order to provide that
Simplicity itself can be a complex set
of specifications that need to be
implemented and does provide us you know
some constraint rates up into the
application layer around those apis as
well so it's one of those things that
for us has been a key foundational piece
in be able to build things like ipfs
initially it was bundled into ipfs and
was split out as a separate layer this
set of components and and now other
projects like ethereum 2 are using lip
P2P even though they don't necessarily
have ipfs or something like that built
in so using that underlying toolkit it
also has a pub sub a publish Subscribe
Feature so you can do messaging where
yeah where you can you know subscribe
and publish messaging and distribute
information that is maybe short-lived
and not immutably referenceable the way
that ipbs is and one of the key pairings
that we see a lot is ipfs you know
publishing data to ipfs and then sharing
those cids over a pub sub channel the
P2P and there you get this really nice
feedback loop and application model
around nodes that are participating
around the given application and when
changes happen they get notified over
that Pub sub channel of hey here's the
new CID nikhail updated his profile
photo here's the new CID for it so you
get that type of functionality which has
been pretty complementary and has led to
some really interesting applications so
you mentioned that uh lip p2b is kind of
built and you it's being used by the
projects so that does that mean it's
kind of like distributed separately from
ipfs can I just go directly and load the
lip b2p library and use it in my
application yeah you can go to the
pdp.io
script implement
ation available on npm you can integrate
into zero libraries it works all the way
out into the web layer but of course any
web content code has constraints on what
network connectivity is available so you
have to do things like you know set up
webrtc or websocket connection for
people to connect outside of your web
page for the rest of the network right
so lip b2p is primarily focused on the
JavaScript and web layer web Community
it's not not kind of I can't kind of
like take this and write a c application
with it oh no no absolutely like the
rest implementation and the go
implementation or kind of the the
network have you you know heavy lifters
for the ipms implementations in those
languages it's language agnostic
toolkit for building transport agnostic
applications I just noted that one of
the places where the p2b has to operate
quite differently is when you actually
publish it on the web content right you
got fetch lab RTC websockets and browser
determines uh you know won't let you
open up a listening tsp socket from a
web page and that's probably a good
thing right so you mentioned that
lipitupi is mainly the way I understood
it is it's kind of like an abstraction
over the network stack right so you
don't really care about how the message
gets communicated to the other side the
p2b kind of tickles handles that you
have a standard API of saying hey okay
this is this is a message send it
somehow yeah right now coming back to
the ipfs relationship so does lip P2P
actually contain the code or the parts
of ibfs that relate to you know the
distributed hash table and connecting to
other nodes and how that hash table is
made maintained yeah so the ipfs
implementation that has the DHT
functionality right basically constructs
that using lip P2P components Okay cool
so this is kind of a little bit of a
tangent but I wanted to kind of go into
that a little bit as well so we've been
talking about DHT and we've been we've
kind of expanded it into a distributed
hash table I'm sure some of our
listeners would love to understand what
is a distributed hash table and why is
that kind of like the way we are
communicating with or discovering nodes
can you talk a little bit about that
yeah I'm probably not the best person to
Define what a distributed hash table is
it's basically given a network of
computers they're sharing information
about state that allows you to
understand what is where on that Network
at a high level that's probably enough
for your Builders and how a set of ipfs
nodes can share State such as hey I have
these sets of addresses or they have
those sets of addresses and so for IPs
it serves a key purpose in that that
ability to share that state across a
broad number of nodes in that Network
allows us to Route users to content
quickly and efficiently so using the
Academia DHD algorithm you can say hey
who's holding X and you can get there in
a very short period of time without
having to say do a full search
exhaustive search of the network right
that actually brings up a slightly
interesting follow-up which is so if
I've got my application my ipfs I've
written my own ipfs application using
lip P2P and I want to connect it to the
ipfs network right where do I kind of
start I mean shouldn't I get some part
of the DHT or how do I actually figure
out which node to start with
so yes we have what are called the
bootstrap nodes and typically anybody
who maintains an ipfs implementation
will usually have a configuration file
that has a set of bootstrap nodes and
these are publicly available nodes at
either vertical Labs runs or other
people run where over time we've either
learned that they have the level of
resilience and availability to be there
and they will then connect you to more
nodes also once you are connected to the
DHC you will learn about more nodes so
the way that Loop P2P connectivity model
for ipfs anyway and the way it uses the
P2P works is that it tries to keep a
number of nodes a low Watermark and a
high water mark a range in a number of
nodes that is permanently connected to
not permanently then it stays connected
to so some some might drop off let's say
you have a minimum connectivity 200
nodes I want to be able to have it
connectivity to 200 nodes at all times
to increase the performance the
probability that any requests I make are
serviced it performantly how do they
tell if I have got connectivity to 200
nodes is that like a heartbeat or some
kind of way to kind of tell whether okay
the 200 nodes that I'm supposed to be
connected to who are still alive yeah
yeah so the ipfest node is basically a
Daemon that runs and maintains
connectivity to those nodes and so using
the ipfs CLI there's a whole list of
commands that you can use with active s
CLI that will give you the state of your
current connection connection to the
network you can everything do everything
from like diagnose the availability of a
given CID you can say hey ipfs tell me
how many nodes on the network are
currently serving the CID and so there's
everything from connectivity and State
Management to data availability on the
network globally to commands to
introspect your local data store what do
I have how big is it uh things like that
and so that is a way where you can say
hey tell me how many nodes am I
currently connected to ipfs companion is
a browser extension that is a companion
to your local ipfs node and it does
things like it has an ambient display
and the number of connections to peers
that you currently have but the way that
that connectivity is managed is let's
say let's say 10 peers drop off ipfest
will then get more peers ask the network
for more Peters until it gets back up to
that range of healthy connectivity that
it wants to maintain so and that's one
of the reasons why you know when we
think about what ipfs is often people
think about running an IPS node which is
like running a server that connects to a
bunch of other servers and is available
to them and answering their requests
which running a server isn't ideally the
ideal architecture for all use cases it
is ideal if you want to actually have a
high availability connection you know
you maybe want more decentralization and
you're not so worried about the
centralization aspect you're like no I'm
cool with some centralization that's
fine that hybrid mode for active passes
totally legitimate and so designing a
software architecture for a service like
that has to be respectful of local use
cases of local computational and
resource requirements things like mobile
like I mentioned having you know 200
persistent connections from a mobile
phone it's not going to last long right
but it might be fine for for their
laptop that's plugged in and you and
you're doing a bunch of stuff that you
want to pull down video or something
like that so it really depends on the
use case that you have and iqbs is
honestly itself likely PDP is a toolkit
for building peer-to-peer applications
ipf itself is a data and distribution
and addressing toolkit you know that
when you talked about what are the best
practices for posting an image or
publishing image should I do make sure
six nodes have it or 12 notes have it or
ten nodes have it and it really it
really depends on the use case and ipfs
is not idiomatic necessarily about the
application layer like HTTP it's like
hey here's some Basics on how to do
addressing here are some things you can
do around level of connectivity or the
things that may be specific to the
environment that you're running it in
but it's not going to tell the
application layer up above how it should
behave too much as long as it meets
those basic requirements it's around the
addressing of data access that that's
where really a lot of that value comes
from awesome cool I think we've been
discussing for a while now and I kind of
looked at the time and we've been
chatting for about over an hour so I
think let's let's kind of like wrap
things up a little bit I think one of my
last questions essentially was be around
as an application developer how do I
actually can I leverage or make use of
ipfs and lip P2P is there kind of like a
easy method for me to kind of start
getting into this technology would it be
better to use like build a website or a
web application or do you think maybe a
More Level CLI application or a desktop
application is the way to go I think it
depends on what your background
experience and interests are so you know
web devs that want to get there that
just want to publish some websites to
ipfs services like fleek.com really make
it easy where they hook up into your
GitHub CI like they'll automatically
publish they'll update your ipns name
they'll update your ensn name even so
making your website available on ipfest
for static content and static web pages
totally easy to go that route just fun
first way then you could share it with
people and send them to that address or
IP Nesta right if you want to install
IPS desktop that's an easy way to
install basically like an electron based
tray application you can see how many
peers you're connected to you can upload
download files that also installs the
CLI so then you can start playing around
with the CLI and start introspecting
your connection to the network asking
the network for data publishing and
seeing how it works that's another way
if you want to get a little bit of both
worlds the brave web browser actually
has ipms built in so you can actually
download an install Brave if you load an
ipfs address in Brave it will ask you
what oh we'll just connect to an ipfs
HTTP Gateway by default but we'll ask
you would you like to install a full
ipfs node and it actually downloads and
runs the go implementation what we call
Kubo implementation of ipfs and then
manages that service it manages it for
you so it'll spin it up turn it up and
down uh you can go to you know Brave
colon ipfs and manage your node from
there you can see how much data it's
hosting and that allows you to natively
inside Brave load then view ipfs data
you can save data to your local ipfs
node through Brave like right click on
an image and save it there and things
like that so that's a pretty fun and
easy way to get started that doesn't
even require any developer capabilities
but you want to build apps that's a
pretty good way and then lastly I think
you know those are two more things rust
ipfs definitely is something there's one
called iro iroh there's a new
implementation of ipfs and rust and a
lot of people are really excited about
and then JS ipfs says the implementation
in JavaScript and there that is a entire
toolkit of different libraries that make
it super easy to use npm and whatever
your entire JavaScript build environment
is to be able to work with ipfs and
that's both server side and client-side
implementations as well okay cool thank
you Detroit it was a great conversation
is there anything in this episode that I
missed that you would would like to talk
about or do you think we've done a good
job of covering what ipfs is we covered
some ground for sure okay we covered a
lot of it you know one thing if people
want to learn more we just had ipfs amp
which is over 500 people that gathered
to talk about ipfs loads and loads of
tracks and talks all those talks are on
YouTube and those are available to watch
if you want to learn more basically the
entire universe of ipfs is this the set
of speakers all the tracks for ipbs cam
easy way they have like 101 level
curriculum 201 level curriculum and then
all kinds of different sub things there
was an entire lid P2P Day so a whole lot
if you want to learn more about looking
to be there as well nice okay thank you
Dietrich for coming on software
engineering radio I had a great time
talking with you thanks thanks for
having me
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening